i think it's good to do
one long meditation first and
uh so i thought i would go to the
gom the stages of meditation by
kamalashina
and i thought you'd like to just hear
what it sounds like
because this is the book in three parts
three short books
which are the basis of all meditation in
tibet
and the basis of this poster
so
i'm going to go to the third go room
because that's the one that talks about
technique the most
okay
the the first book talks
mainly about compassion almost the whole
book is about compassion
and it's very beautiful it would be nice
to translate someday
it's very beautiful he goes through a
long description of the
sufferings of the lower realms so
there's a long description of the hell
realms and
how people are suffering from uh burning
and freezing
and then there's a long description of
the
spirit hungry spirits and
how much they suffer from hunger and
thirst and uncertainty
and then there's a long description of
uh animal realm
and how they mainly
hurt each other that it's a realm of
where
beings are hurting each other eating
each other
then he gets to the human realm and he
says
he asks a rhetorical question he says is
it so much different from those other
three
he says people are getting burned and
frozen
you know in wars for example and
people are have hunger and thirst all
over the world
like hungry ghosts and
people are the society is abusing
people and making them work like animals
rosa knows about that uh
but you know is it so different
in our realm you know people are being
burned
people are being enslaved and people are
hurting each other
and people are hungry and he goes into
you know
almost the whole book is about
compassion
and then he says compassion is the karma
for shaman okay compassion is the karma
for shambhat
and it's also the motivation
to get shamanta because then you can
become a buddha but with shamatha you
need
understanding emptiness so the second
gom the second book of his
meditation
the second book of his trilogy is the
emptiness all emptiness
it's all about vipassiana
and it's interesting that somebody
should do a study some graduate student
at the sedona college
should do a study between 9 and an
earlier above chroma
and earlier gomuram which was written by
nagarjuna
so nagarjuna wrote a book called stages
of meditation
and that's mostly a study of of
vipassana of emptiness
and it'd be very interesting to compare
the second book of the trilogy to
to nagarjuna i think he maybe that's why
he named his book the same
so he lived fifteen hundred years after
nagarjuna uh so it's kind of cool
uh then the third book is technique
meditation technique and so we
i want you to think of shamatha in terms
of uh
the karma that you need to get it
it's at the bottom cause of course and
then there's
uh conditions like a nice beach in
thailand
where it's quiet where you can meditate
easily
and it's it's pleasant and then
inner technique mental techniques so
and if you think about it uh
these two are caused by this one you see
what i mean
the karma creates the conditions the
karma creates a nice meditation cottage
at diamond mountain
i like michael with said unique that's
such a good
that's such a good publicity thing we
may not
we may be rustic but we're unique
you gotta have something so so the
compassion
creates the circumstances you know
it stops the garbage trucks outside your
house at
six o'clock in the morning they break
down at the end of the street
if you're in new york and then
that also causes the success of the
inner techniques of trying to detect
dullness trying to detect agitation
trying to block them
okay so so he gives it
this kind of causal thing the compassion
creates the conditions and and allows
the technique to work okay the inner
technique
it's very cool so uh
i thought you might like to hear
something we'll start on his technique
from his own book this is the mother
book of all meditation in tibet
he bases his uh largely on a sutra which
one
what sutra talks about meditation
king of concentration king of meditation
so it'd be fun to go through that suture
someday
you know okay so here i'm just going to
read you a small piece and then we'll
meditate okay
because he this is he's starting on his
technique third
third book of the trilogy
there's a fourth book i haven't explored
yet it's a
mysterious okay it's called meditation
for yogis i don't know
okay
if you want to get shamatha and
vipassiana
you have to collect the karma tsutun
number tapala
one of those causes is not disturbing
the minds of other people
okay not disturbing the minds of other
people and i think if you're going to be
a good meditator
to make the karma you have to be super
sensitive
to other people's reactions to what you
say and what you do
you see so you watch you learn to watch
them
you pick up signs like their eyes go
like that
you know like you're like would you like
to make me hot chocolate and they're
like
yeah yeah
and then you get if you're gonna be a
good meditator
you have to be very sensitive to how
other people are feeling
and and and your whole life is uh
watching how they feel observing what
they need
and making them happy you know even
little things like
how much honey do they take in their
coffee and stuff like that
and then those are the causes when you
get on your cushion
the techniques work for you you see what
i mean so
in dci language we call it crystal legs
it means it comes from a scripture
everybody's in here between the
sides of your skull it's as if everyone
has a leg
a beautiful swiss geneva like
you know totally clean pure and they
walk around with this lake in their mind
and then uh if they get upset in the
morning you know
like if they can't find their toothpaste
then their
mind gets a little like like geneva with
a breeze
on it and then the first person they
meet whose
mind is still it
it uh spreads it's uh what do you call
it
catchy contagious yeah like if i'm a
little off balance and i meet you
and it seems to be the more off balanced
person
affects the less off balanced person so
if my mind's a little bit upset because
i couldn't find my toothpaste this
morning
then and i meet the first time i meet
somebody in the morning
my shaky leg shakes up their leg
so so that the karmic cause of shamanta
is to do the opposite even if you're not
feeling well
or you're not feeling so happy or
something just went wrong
in your life which happens once in a
while
uh you try to make other people's minds
calm
even if you don't feel so calm okay and
on the outside you're just like
very common you know on the inside
you're like worrying about this cabinet
the water broke
you know but outside you're just like
yeah everything's fine
and then that respect for other people's
peace of mind
is the karmic cause of shamatha and
without that the other two don't matter
you can have a good cushion and you can
study the meditation poster for a year
and you're still going to have lousy
meditation because you don't have the
karma cause
okay the base cause uh nepa
is and the second karmic cause first
karmic cause is
respecting other people's peaceful mind
and then the second karma calls this
ninja tumble
compassion a concern for other people's
ultimate welfare
not just that they're happy this morning
but uh
that they don't go to the hell realms or
or that they reach uh
so you got to get really good at
explaining the pen right
you could keep some but people you could
keep a lot of people out of the hell
okay so just bore people to death teach
it over and over
okay uh
carry one with you
chambo kittens
have this intention to save the world by
becoming a buddha
don samban of gombela john
and before you meditate finish the
process of tur
sam gom okay uh go to
lots of classes go to as many classes as
you can study as many books as you can
then some like what you hear in the
class
thrash it thrash it or thrush it thrash
it out with other people
in a coffee shop at the julieta blue sky
dome
we're trying to build a coffee shop in
sedona next to the college because
that's where people that's called
to some some means uh you sit with your
friends and you say yes you michael said
this thing this morning but it doesn't
make any sense to me
and your friend says yeah it didn't make
any sense so don't worry though
and you know so
but you threat you you work with your
friends and you you
you tear it apart and you work it out
until you're satisfied with it and then
gum
then you can meditate on it then come la
sheila in another of his books he
he has a long thing about don't go into
a meditation without the turn of some
you know that's really the third one
meditate on
after you've questioned it after you've
heard about it
but but don't go into meditation with no
ammunition
don't go into meditation with nothing to
to meditate about
okay to you're going to meditate about
what you discussed with your friends
after you heard it in the class
so he he's very adamant don't go into a
meditation with no
object you know and i think that happens
a lot in the west
like in china you meditated for 5000
years
in america we meditated for 50 years
one percent and so we have all these
weird ideas about meditation you know
and and and
oftentimes in in america we don't have
training
so we go into a meditation with nothing
to meditate about we're just like
you know but we don't have an object in
mind okay
choosing the object is half of the
meditation challenge
yogi okay any yogi who wants to meditate
talkman first they should chow
chi up the time finish all your projects
before you go into meditation
or you know get you you know
finish all the word don't go into
meditation with some work on your mind
okay finish it first he says this is a
kamala sheila
this is really weird it took me like
half an hour figured out i was asking
veronica by the way veronica says she
will give
massages to whoever needs them give your
name to
jigman you're first on the list i think
really cool you asked i think
so she can't do endless it takes like
two hours but
if you're if you're having a hard time
and you're not
you're you're your body's hurting or or
you feel nervous
then uh give your name to jake may and
we'll schedule you
we'll try to get you in for a massage
okay we have an expert here
okay um did he say
chill out choke
you should go to a yiddi one way choke
what's choc pa payata cha
good he's my human dictionary
chuck means direction you young
like you guys know young jumper
where it's the kind of love that sees
everyone as their own child
so beautiful that's beautiful so you
mean it's beautiful
so what's a young choke beautiful
direction yeah go to a fantastic place
then he describes it it's really funny
he's kind of funny
i don't know why i have the karma to
meet him uh
it's okay if you go to a place that's
filled with shang and qi
if your room is full of poo-poo and
pee-pee that's fine
that's an attractive place okay
i'm like what and then he says but there
should be
no diet silma diet ceremony
means a cactus thorn okay
noise okay so an attractive place in
meditation
means quiet it can be
filled with poopoo beefy that's okay
because you're not going to worry about
that that's not going to bother you you
can
clip your nose but it should be quiet
you know that's what a meditators
what do you call it bread and butter is
a quiet place
you know it's a quiet place and this
diamond mountain is quiet
it's got rocks and snakes and cactus but
it's quiet
okay it's super this is the quietest
place i've ever been to
okay so so this is a beautiful place
okay
then have this intention to
bring everybody to enlightenment and
we're going to talk about that a lot in
the diamond color sutra today
okay in the chin
youngsters
bring up thoughts of compassion for
for how much pain is in the minds of
most people
okay now he says there's certain things
you should do
before you start to meditate look now
we're getting into technique okay
number one see if you recognize them
you know this yeah all the blues in the
ten directions yeah that's how the
sojourn starts in the monastery three
thousand
monks going
and they always take a young man who
whose voice hasn't changed yet
and he goes he sings it alone he sings
the first verse alone
it means all the buddha's in the ten
directions john jusemba
what's a five-part prostration yeah two
hands
two knees and your head okay that's a
full prostration
right well i guess it could not be
okay so bow down to the buddhism
buddhist office
first first meditation first thing you
do in the medicine
second sangeet and charity
shocks come young day
you can put an image in front of you
like a statue or a painting
or you can imagine them in front of you
and chinooki means as as as
as much as your means allow
uh chipper yeah
put offerings out for them okay flowers
water cakes
we have a pineapple upside down cake
chipper okay make offerings
third one rangi dikba shop
yeah confess your negativities okay
shark means what do you know yeah like
when you take a hatchet and you split
wood
and it goes what so it means uh
be honest and be be sincere you can do
it in your mind you know not to tell
anybody what a nasty thing you did
yesterday when you're by yourself in
your room
but when you're talking to your llama in
your head
you should shock the because they can
see it anyway
you might as well shakba
uh fourth dua tadaki cinema jason
yeah rejoice in all the good of of
yourself and other people
what are those it's pretty much the
georgia
okay it's pretty much the first of the
three treasures
okay there's two that he didn't mention
yeah ask him to stay ask him to teach
and then and then dedicate
okay he didn't mention this but you can
see how
uh
700 years before tonkapa the
the georgia is forming up
okay last thing then we'll meditate okay
i'm just going to give you a little
a little gomuram every day babanakrama
uh then shindu jamba
tewala then here means a den
like dorje then yeah a seat
a seat uh asana
it's it's bhadrasana right asana can
mean seed also
um
means soft like silk or velvet okay
dewa comfortable okay
on a comfortable meditation seat and you
have to find your own and keep
experimenting keep trying different ones
after 10 years you find the one that's
best for you
i love these i i highly recommend these
these have uh
what's inside buckwheat uh it have
little grains inside
so my butt is like all messed up and
and it it
it it takes the shape of your butt you
know so i really like this one but i
have a friend who uses a piece of wood
and some people llama devorah has three
cushions and i like to put one of these
here on my lap because then my hands are
like this and they're not like this
so i have two of these i put one
here i put it here and i stretch it out
to here and i can
and then my hands are here and they're
not like i'm not like that
but you you have to experiment but he
says
john dewa uh comfortable and soft
okay then he said there's this daddy i'm
gonna show you a picture of him
where is he
there's an old picture so there's an old
daddy
his name is viral channa
you see where we're going and he says
viral chenna always sits in a full lotus
okay so look at his feet he's he says
but
lara chen is a good example for us when
we want to meditate
his the way he holds his feet is very
good
you know
uh so kumo tung means a full lotus
kutung
or tabulam
yeah half lotus okay so even in ancient
sanskrit it's
it's half lotus tu young either one
full lotus or half lotus but he says
half lotus is best and and and that
that's
use the one that you see by china doing
okay which
foot is um
he's got his left foot up first
okay if you want to have a useless
argument with a hindu
you can do the right foot left foot
thing it i don't think it matters too
much
but you pull the left foot in first
and then you pull the right foot in but
but like diamond mitre does it the
opposite and that's fine
he seems to be okay
but if you want to you know get
sectarian you can argue about that
okay second
so that's how to put your legs and
that's probably why the eight-point
posture became called
china's posture it was maybe it was
because of the of the lotus
and then it got confused to everything
you see i mean i think so
uh mick hajang miyet
don't open your eyes too wide and don't
close them too tight
okay focus them loosely on
on the level of your nose not on the tip
of your nose because that will hurt your
eyes okay
and some people who didn't know sanskrit
very well
they read this and they're like
it means focus here don't focus on the
ground
and don't focus on your hands like focus
here
which is what you're doing you're
thinking about your boyfriend in high
school
okay you're not looking at the ceiling
your eyes are unfocused and that's
good for concentration
okay it's not you're not you're not
looking at the ceiling
okay your eyes are unfocused okay
you can play around that you can use
that as a durstine yoga also you can
play around with it
and see how it how it feels okay so
that's your eyes
we got how many so far two things right
third one lu hajang
okay so this refers to your spine
keep it straight that's kinesthetic
misapprehension i remember the word
uh it's what's that guy's name i don't
know he's a dance master who died long
ago but
i mean of course your spine is curved in
three places but something but
but it feels straight
huh challenging no not possible
he he teaches a special technique
alexander technique uh
jamba nang du shakti and then collect
your thoughts and we're going to
talk more about that because the buddha
collects his thoughts
next in the diamond cutter situation
we'll talk about that
next chalkbon
yeah it's interesting though because he
uses the verb samapati
which is the verb for balanced
meditation but he's here he's saying
make sure your shoulders are level so
the word for meditation in sanskrit
means keep it level okay
so don chu so means your teeth and chew
means your lips
tamel pershaco tamel means
normal right it's a tantric expression
right tamil nancien
to be attached to the normal but here it
means
just the way it always you know don't
think about it just
let them relax don't don't
don't do anything with them wherever
your teeth go
let them go wherever your tongue and
your lips go let them go there okay so
that was the
sixth one i think
next to you
uh the passing of your breath in and out
should not have dog yeah it should be
silent there's two levels of that one is
a growth
noise that you make when you breathe and
one is the noise of
air passing your hairs and your nose
and as you get better at meditation you
will detect a second
and then it will stop okay so don't make
don't let your breath be noisy numb
don't let it be irregular should be
the inhale and exhale should be smooth
and like don't get uh like don't have a
coffee before you meditate and then your
breath is like
a little bit crazy means crazy
monkeys are called mirga apes apes are
called mere good
crazy crazy people so your breath
shouldn't be
shaky okay tangy
chinese
as far as you can do it slow your breath
down
and make long exhales okay long exhales
so so that's your first taste of the gom
rim okay
okay and we'll we'll try now we'll try
okay he's missing one of the eight
i figured it out because i had a half an
hour and i had my computer
yeah your hands he doesn't talk about
your hands so
okay you can write to him and complain
okay okay
i i was like he's missing one but i
couldn't figure it out for a while
probably the student forgot to write it
down
okay so let's let's meditate
here there's a there's a little guy here
yeah just push it down yeah
you okay ginger better
i think she got a little dizzy
okay
so as far as technique uh
we did yesterday just
letting stillness be the object of your
meditation
so the stillness of your body
and i'd like you to do that every day
okay this week
do at least like 20 minutes
and take as your object your own body
and focus on your body and see
if you cannot move any part of it like
your eyebrow or your fingers
or okay a little bit of movement in your
where is okay your chest you have to
breathe
by the way if your meditation gets
really good the breath stuffs
which proves that you are not sustained
by oxygen
okay
so starting today and every day
one pretty long session 15 20 minutes on
where the body is the object of the
meditation and you don't move it
now we're going to add to that another
meditation of about
20 minutes about your
breath watching your breath as a
as a preliminary as a warm-up okay
but i want you to do it a special way
this is uh
from naropa and
i find it very helpful for focusing
in meditation okay so try this out this
week give it a try
okay this is a special way to watch your
breath
so bring your mind to your forehead
and feel your two eyebrows
and then go towards the center of your
head
and you see it between the two eyebrows
there's a spot
and then go up the forehead
about an inch like a centimeter and a
half i guess
and focus on that spot like a third eye
bruvar madhya
and if you want to get really fancy go
into your skull
about half an inch and the focus gets
very nice because you're touching a
chakra
minor chakra
so you can move your focus around
like a flashlight
that part of your head inside your skull
maybe half an
inch but see if you can find a
a place with your focus that when you
bring your mind there
right away you feel deeper the
meditation feels deeper
so experiment go to the left go to the
right go up go down
go in go deeper
come out see if you can find a spot
in the lower part of your forehead
between your eyebrows on the on that
line
where it gets a lot easier to
concentrate so i'm going to give you a
few minutes here
see if you can find this place
don't scrunch up your forehead don't
don't get your forehead should be loose
you shouldn't wrinkle your forehead
like stay loose
and stay focused
we'll stay here for 5-10 minutes
move around see if you find a better
spot
everybody's body is different
when you find the spot relax stay there
and don't don't wrinkle your forehead
don't tighten your forehead
now keep your eyes closed but please
add the breath the exhale
coming out of that place in your
forehead so
the breath is coming out of your nose
but imagine that it's coming out of the
place in your forehead
and when you exhale
the breath is coming out of your
forehead
and you can play around with
extending it further and further so
in meditation long exhales tend to calm
you down
and long inhales tend to agitate you
so focus on a long
slow leisurely
exhale through the
space in your forehead and ignore the
gross breath coming through your
nostrils
this is where your prana is leaving the
body when you breathe
we'll stay here for about i don't know
five minutes or something
long exhales to your forehead don't
worry about the inhales
try not to move your body
then slowly open your eyes
take a stretch you're about halfway
halfway through
next part i'd like you to imagine that
the
the breath is coming out here because
you're pushing it from here okay
so lower belly like even below your
navel okay so imagine that you are
squeezing here and it it
you're pulling in here and it causes the
breath to go out like
and the breath comes out here so it goes
up the body up the spine and
comes out here okay so be aware of the
tightening your your lower stomach
there's a word in yoga also
it's kunda or something i don't know
i'll look it up
yeah same thing there's a center here
and you
squeeze it in and then it
forces the prana to come out of your
forehead okay so you're gonna
be just be aware of the tightening of
the lower stomach
lower abdominal abdominal muscles
and then that brings the breath out here
okay
so we'll do that we'll do that for the
same like
five minutes okay so so now you're
pressing in the lower abdomen
and it forces the prana out your
forehead okay
and that's super good for your health
okay it's like really really good for
your health
ladies health especially men also
okay uh it does something to you
okay okay ready
okay try not to move because when you
move it it disturbs other people
okay
if your body hurts tell it to go to hell
just divorce yourself from the body okay
i think if you're really gonna meditate
seriously you have to learn to
to ignore it okay when your knees
hurt or your feet fall asleep like don't
get up
fast right hustle but uh
there'll be some pin pins and needles
and pins
and then it goes away and then you can
sit there for five hours because
you can't feel anything but you got to
get through that
that pins and needles okay
okay here we go please don't move
find that place in your forehead
move your focus around until you touch
some until
you feel something
that takes your mind deeper
try higher try lower try deeper
keep your eyelids soft keep your
forehead soft
if you tighten up you'll get a headache
and the exhales are coming out now
follow the exhales out
long relaxed exhales
function exhale
and don't worry about the inhales
and now connect it to your lower abdomen
feel how it contracts
and then the prana comes out the
forehead
i will stay here for about five minutes
contract exhale contract exhale
don't go crazy just a light contraction
so
hmm
okay you can open your eyes
can you stand up yeah it's okay be
careful
you want to wait for a minute okay just
stay there
now we're going to work on the inhale
okay
come closer and i want you to
feel it coming down your back
okay so there you have two side channels
here right
you're done pingala then uh i want when
you do the inhale
i want you to feel like energy
collecting in your shoulder here
and then it it it gets thinner and
thinner and thinner
and then it it connects into the belly
and it comes out again
so the exhale is coming up through the
sushumna what's the other name
so it's uh the exhale is going to come
up the middle of the spine okay
but the inhale like feel the energy the
product
coming like your shoulder blade is a
triangle right
so it's it's a little bit wider here and
then it it gets thinner as it goes down
okay and then your belly pushes it out
again
okay so that's going to open up your two
side channels
so the inhale's coming down the eda
and the pingula okay inhale's coming
down the two side channels
then they down here they connect into
the central channel
so when you exhale your lower belly goes
in
and the and the breath comes out and
then comes out here
okay so don't worry about it coming in
here or here or something like that
you can think of it coming in at the top
of your shoulders okay
and feel it wide and then it gets
narrower and then it comes out of here
okay all right
then we have a whole cycle like the
breath coming in
and then it's connecting into the
central channel and then and then you're
pushing
and it comes out here okay good
feel okay any questions
any questions don't get tight here okay
don't like
no because it it when you focus here it
tends to get tight
and then you're going to have a headache
okay question
which one uh
it's like you have wings in the back
it's like you have angel wings really
you can imagine that
it's very nice like like you're like
you know like you have wings like an
angel and you feel the
air when you breathe in it's coming
here down from
like this yeah so don't think two little
tiny side channels like that
sink broad at the shoulders
in the back and then it collects down
and then it comes up
to the center channel it comes out here
okay so it's like
okay like that cool and you'll find a
nice effect on your side channels
okay and you can think of wings
and open your uh what do you call
shoulder blades
when you inhale like
i mean not so exaggerated
hustle when you say contraction
of the abs yeah it's just the natural
cooling yeah it's not like
yeah don't go but a slight
just a slight thing you know and this
muscle will get stronger
the first few days it'll feel a little
uncomfortable and you're hurt here
like but don't go crazy the whole thing
don't never go crazy
in meditation like don't go
because you'll get sick and you'll
something will happen
you'll get constipated maybe some of the
three retreats
if you misplace the focus you're like
can't poop for three days
no no perennium yeah not between your
legs
not that part then you'll get the
constipation
okay so don't don't try to tighten that
not perineum
uh lower belly we say uh
four tun
14 below the belly button so everybody's
belly button is different
some people hear some people here
it should be just below your belly
button and very gentle
okay if you go really crazy you you're
going to do something
you won't be able to swallow or
don't go crazy in meditation because
you'll hurt yourself
then you run around without your clothes
on
we start
you're following your mind singing
you're following your
breath with your mind yeah yeah like
don't and don't pause you don't have to
punch it becomes
a cycle okay but try to feel this thing
with your shoulders like
like angel really like angel wings you
know like you're open
but not like that okay i mean but just
in your mind you're like
okay what should be longer to inhale or
exhale
yeah always focus on the exhale then you
won't go crazy okay
if you're like
you'll get nervous you'll get nervous
and and you'll have problems
it's very sensitive all this machine is
uh
you can you can get cuckoo okay
yeah yeah i'd like you to follow it
pretty closely
if you can
it's kind of more vague in the back on
the inhale
there's just this kind of a feeling of
almost like wings opening you know
and then you press in and then it comes
out okay
cool yeah so i guess i'm still not clear
where the
inhale originates yeah so don't don't
think here
don't think here don't think here vague
someplace vague behind the back of your
upper shoulders
uh i would put it more in front of them
because i see it on my spine
and i would like you to put it a little
forward to that
should we feel
the swaddling
you know what i mean then
yeah as it comes up but in the back it
comes from
yeah in the spine uh
you don't have to think like this you
don't have to think like that just
you can later but it's easier if you
just like
and it runs from the back right it's a
half inch in front of the spine
this much in front of the spine yeah
what do they call it in medicine
anterior interior
this this side of the spine
from the two sides
uh it comes down i want you to feel it
like this
and then you know like under the sink
there's
hot water and cold water and they
connect to the
the drain under the sink it goes like
this
so down below your navel
the two side channels connect to the
center channel like that
it it it looks like oh
it looks like that you see
so the two side channels come down and
they connect to the central channel
okay below yeah below the navel
yeah that's where you're going to press
him
but don't get too clear on it don't
don't make it too complicated because
you'll get a stomach ache or something
let it be a little vague okay
you're ready to try inhaling angel
inhales
then focus next time
we're not meditating yet we're just
getting ready
okay maybe tomorrow we meditate okay
okay so we have two meditations so far
what's the first one
yeah focus on your body like a stone
like a statue that's gonna be like 20
minutes
and then then this one you're going to
do and then i'm going to teach you some
ching kanjing meditations today also
okay ready
here we go yes please
you know when a yoga teacher says pull
your navel towards your spine
that's that's pretty much it okay
but don't go crazy because you'll you'll
hurt something
you won't be able to poo-poo for three
days okay
don't never do extreme things okay just
be like fun
okay if you feel nervous stop
go for a walk if you feel shaky
stop go for a walk don't continue just
quit
right away because i have a friend he's
michael wick
you know him he did it wrong
in 1972. he's still sick
he's still sick you know him he's like
this
you know he my llama taught him
this thing and he said don't don't do
too hard and he did it too hard
he was in hell and uh he's still sick
okay how old is he he's like 70 now
and he's still a little bit shaky okay
so don't go crazy if you feel anything
stop make yourself a big
popcorn no oil oil is very good
okay if you feel nervous or something
have greasy noodle
lots of olive oil lots of okay and then
everything relax
okay but if you feel like this then you
have to stop you have to stop
okay go for a walk how long you have to
do it to really like god
seek or something
he did it for weeks he did it for six
weeks or something
without my teacher there my teacher went
away he did it
my teacher said don't do it too hard he
did it too hard
i think it was about two months so don't
worry
in three days you're not going to get
sick you might get constipation
okay you ready that's the last one okay
nice angel wings and come out to the
forehead
and do not wrinkle the forehead and do
not tighten the forehead
keep it loose okay and this is just
slight
you know it's like a butterfly
what do you call butterflies
there's one coming up in the in the tin
hunting okay
breathe down through your wings
press the lower belly
the exhale comes up to your spine
and out your forehead and just enjoy it
okay i'll tell you when to stop you
don't have to worry
i won't leave you here
right
okay you can relax okay
let's do about 10 minutes at diamond
cutter and then we'll take a break
michael and melissa made you green
drinks
and some oj and some ginger tea okay
uh so we left the buddha
was just going into meditation right
he washed his feet put away his bowl
and sat down on the cushion that the
gods had put there for him
on the floor to be humble
and then the sutra says he collected his
thoughts
he collected his thoughts did you get
the text or
the sutra well i did get it but he
didn't have time
okay so tomorrow
can you get it ready for tomorrow what
do you want to do without
talking well talk as much as you have to
get it done
in four languages
okay you guys work it out oh give it to
michael
one of my bosses used to say do they
necessary
that's all he's saying do they
necessarily go out for coffee
okay uh
then what does he collect his thoughts
on and
master kamala sheila says on the dungeon
so dungan means his lineage
means it should not be interrupted so
his past prayers to come to this world
and help people then
you know what does the buddha think
about after breakfast
he's thinking how can i prevent my
lineage from being broken in this world
how can i continue
my teaching lineage on this planet
because that was what i always wanted
i wanted to start a teaching lineage and
then i wanted it to continue
on so that's his first thought during
the meditation
then suddenly 1 250 monks show up
okay
it's it's confusing in the tibetan
because it's up to
so normally then how many thousands
comes after the thousands like
no that's not right anyway it's a
confusing number
uh it's 1250 monk show up
along with great bodhisattvas along with
a great number of
great police officers so so master
kamala sheila he's like justin cop he's
like
how come he gets the number for the
monks but he doesn't give the number for
the bodhisattvas you know
why does he say exactly 1 250 monks
came and then he doesn't tell you how
many bodhisattvas and he says
well obviously bodhisattvas haven't
committed to
helping all people some of them are
going to be busy
out teaching in kazakhstan or
southern china or you know the
bodhisattvas because they agreed to help
everybody
we don't know how many are going to show
up because they're out on missions
they're out helping people the monks
they're not
these monks are not like buddy stop they
just show up
they live they live around there there's
1250 monks
and they all they all came but the
bodhisattvas some of them were out on
missions
to help other people so that's why
there's no exact number for the
bodhisattvas
then he goes into some cool stuff if you
care about the scriptures you know
he he's writing in sanskrit right
and he gives some comments about why
monks are called bikshu okay so big shoe
say big shoe
means monk for monk and that's a female
monkeys
yeah so you can't add an eye to a u so
you put an end between
big shoony okay so why are they called
big shoe then
the verb sanskrit is built on roots
there's 800 roots if you memorize 800
roots on the bus going to new york to
you can you can generate sanskrit it's
generative grammar
you can generate the whole language if
you know the roots without seeing the
words
so uh the big shoe
is normally explained as what what's big
yeah normally they say beggar come
lashes says i don't like that that's not
correct
he says bix is the decitative case of
bug which means to share
or it because it means to split because
it means to divide
it means to divide up so bhagavad-gita
bhagavat means you have your blessings
you get your share of blessings it's
similar to countdown in tibetan
okay like you get your share so bhaga
the the root bug which sometimes has a
prenatal bang
means to cut or to divide or to share
and all the words like fract branch
comes from that which means to branch
and fragile comes from that
and fractiles and franga
the latin to to branch or to break
vagina comes from that it means to split
and so bhaga means your share
or to split to split then he says bikshu
which is deciduative which means a
strong desire to split
in sanskrit you double the verb and you
add a s-s-u so it becomes big q
and so he says
big shoe means divorced from their
mental afflictions
divided from their mental afflictions
okay which means all monks and nuns
should be
totally stable and happy but anyway
pretty much they're working on it
they're working on it
so he he explains picture and they come
in a mahasangena right in a in the form
of a
great number of sangha
then he says did you know what sangha
means
and i always assumed it was the
sam which means together and ga which
means to come together
and the greek word is synagogue comes
from that
so sangha and synagogue are related but
but there's a problem because the g is
gha and that gha
in sanskrit is the verb for han it comes
from han
which means to strike or to cut a hinsa
comes from that
the word gun comes from that so han
means to
hurt somebody so he's
kamala shilo is concerned that it's g8
and he says you've got to understand
when you have a strong group of
practitioners together
nobody can hurt them
okay yeah i like it
it's really cool then he says why we
call it mahasanga
either because there's a lot of people
there or the monks and nuns who are
there
that the the group the community
is tight so it's
it's not only a lot of monks and nuns
and and
students but they're tight they're
strong
maha they're big because they're strong
they're tight they work together
okay so they showed up
then they uh they all come over to lord
buddha
and it's not clear but it seems like he
taught the whole sutra in a state of
meditation or something
like the xinjing
similar okay so first everybody comes
and
each monk puts his hand on the seat of
the buddha each monk touches their head
to the feet of the buddha and then they
circle the buddha three times
which is respectful okay and then they
sit down
so this is showing respect to the
teacher and uh
american people freak out if the people
are prostrating to a teacher they say oh
this is a cult and there's a guru and
but it's very normal for buddhists to
show respect to a teacher
and it's very necessary okay so
i will say the americans just have to
get used to it
you know we are not
what they were before we're different
it's a new thing
and we we do some other things and
they're okay
they don't hurt anybody you bow down to
your teacher
this is the buddhist custom okay
but because of the other thing we don't
want to freak people out we can you can
just go like nah
if the people are all going to freak out
if you get down on the floor
then then you should respect their you
shouldn't mess up their crystal leg
okay all right
then one of the monks whose name is
subbudi
which in tibetan is a rabjor
we had a mongol monk in new jersey named
rupture and it's a corruption of rapture
and um
he stands up and he drops his sen
okay watch gail say no just this
mainly this one so they he drops the
he drops the rope from his right
shoulder which is called a
silent bump he he drops the
he drops the shaw which is a sign of
respect
so it means he's going to ask a question
so he drops the shawl
he goes down on his right knee he
genuflects he
he kneels down and then he joins his
pumps so these are three
customs for a buddhist who's going to
ask a question
okay they dropped their like you're not
allowed to wear a hat
you know it's it's bet you take off your
hat or you drop your
stand and then you go down on your right
knee
and then you join your palms and in
buddhism we put the thumbs inside
that's another thing you can fight with
hindus about if you want to
okay it means my hands are not empty i
have something to offer
okay and then you then he asked the
question okay but that whole scene
the master kamala sheila says the whole
point
of everything in this sutra has a
purpose
everything that happens in the sutra has
a purpose
if you have a a really good training in
buddhism
this sutra is alarm room
everything is happening for a reason in
order
you know and if you can follow the
buddha's
you know lsd mine
you know there there's a reason why
everything's happening
you know it's nothing's extra nothing's
by accident
you must respect the teacher or you
won't get any teaching
okay you can't go there and say oh hi
how you doing man
you know like you have to be
respectful and and
after many years i lived with my teacher
for 25 years
in the same house it's hard to be
respectful when you live with somebody
all the time
anyone who's ever been married knows
that and
and it was hard for me uh to be
respectful all the time and then one day
i realized
respect is not outside it's affection
it's affection we were like an old
married couple
you know he'd say uh i'd say
that means i feel like having a tea that
means
give me a break i'll make one in a while
but there's an affection to the whole
thing okay so i think
respect without affection is to me it's
hollow
i don't like it these people who are
like oh my
god you know and then you say would you
mind
putting a curtain on these two windows
by tomorrow
they're like no i'm pt and then it's not
respect
okay seiji you got that you and nick
just a couple of thumbtacks nothing
fancy
and then they then there's an infection
they're like yeah cut me some slack just
not like
let me do it but the day after okay like
but
there's a sweet relationship and not
this sterile
respect without affection okay so
so the point here is that before a
teaching can happen
the student must show some
affectionate respect for the teacher
okay and that might
involve you know making a dirty joke or
something
that's okay you know like a poo poo joke
or something
that's okay that's better than this if
if you're
nervous and and possessive
you know of the teacher
that's very unpleasant you know but if
you're just like hey
hey guess what you want to go out for a
milkshake
we won't tell anybody i'm like yeah
let's do it
okay